Okay, so I'm going to share my screen.
Let me just get it to the right place first.
Okay.
Okay, so for anyone that doesn't know, it is mental health awareness week this
week, which is one of the reasons why I was doing this call.
But also I do want to do them more often as just just the check in part that we
have at the end.
So I think if we could do it once a month, then be really nice just to give
people a space to share, and especially we have new people coming in as we get
to know each other a bit more we can check in with how we felt about the thing
we talked about last session or whatever.
Just nice to have that place to share, isn't it.
Like I said, I'm recording this first bit, but I'm going to stop recording and
then we'll have whatever you want to say is then confidential. So whatever
anybody shares after I've stopped recording, you know, we're all committing to
confidentiality or committing to be respectful and just giving each other a
place to share.
So first I'm going to talk a little bit about mental health, just to kind of
open up this conversation, because it's something that's not talked about
nearly enough.
So I wanted to go through what mental health is, because I know we have to see
that phrase banded about all the time that this unless you work with mental
health, as I do.
And not many people actually know what it is or what it isn't.
And so I think it's good to come back to so mental health is important, of
course, and it's something that everyone has all have mental health, just like
we all have physical health.
It doesn't necessarily mean that there's an issue, it's just health, we all
have it.
It's intrinsically linked to and probably inseparable from physical health.
So, you know, we are not just like a head cut off and then a body.
You know, we are a complex system made up of our brain, you know, our neuro
system, and our brain is always sending messages to our body.
So if we've experienced trauma, or if we have chronic stress or there's other
things going on that's affecting our mental health, it's also affecting our
physical health.
And we see that in things like disease, good issues, sleep problems, you know,
the list is endless.
If you're not looking after your mental health and your physical health will
suffer.
Mental health is on a continuum, so it is, you know, it's ever going up and
down, it's not fixed.
And, you know, we all have times where we have good mental health and we all
have times where it's not so good.
And we're not always in control of that.
It's worth making time for, it's part of being human, something we need to look
after, and this is one of the ways that we can look after it by being in these
spaces and sharing with each other.
And bringing the attention back to ourselves and what we need.
And it's positive and negative, so of course you can have good mental health,
that can also be a good thing.
And it's changeable, it's complex, there are many different things that feed
into it and I'll talk about some of the things in a minute, and it's real, of
course.
And then on the other side, some things that it isn't, so of course it's not a
sign of weakness to struggle with your mental health, you know, we all do, but
one time we're in that part of being human.
It's not shameful, it's not all in your mind, which we tend to tell ourselves
sometimes if we're struggling with things, you know, it is real.
It's not always negative, it's not something you decide to have, so you don't
decide, you know, how your mental health is going to be.
And it's not something to think about only when it feels broken, so you know we
tend to do this and think about mental health only when we're struggling.
You know, it's easy when you're in the profession, like me I'm working every
day in mental health, but that means that every day I'm thinking about it and I
'm grateful for when it's going well I'm thinking about why it's going well and
what I'm doing.
It's good to always think about it.
It doesn't mean if you've got good mental health that you feel good all the
time, that's not true because that's not authentic, good mental health is about
being authentic.
Oh, I missed one yeah it's it's not an interchangeable term with mental illness
so mental health and mental illness are two completely different things, just
like physical health and disease are two different things.
So a mental illness is a long term condition, diagnosable condition but mental
health is we all have it and we're very different things.
And it's not something you can snap out of but it's also not fixed so it can
always get better.
And the last one it's not fake news.
So that's a few things about mental health.
And it's important then to come back to the realization that we find what we
expect to find in the world so we are living with certain lenses on you know
our perception of what's going on around us is about us.
It's not actually about the world, you know if we've grown up feeling scared,
then we come into the world you know our everyday is feeling scared because
that's the glasses that we're wearing.
And so we find what we expect to find we do not see the world as it is but as
we are.
And of course there's a glass half old glass half everything as well.
Just letting a couple of people come in.
So, I think there's only there's only this slide, maybe there's one more, but I
just wanted to talk about a few reasons because it's really good to absolve
ourselves of the responsibility so whatever you're feeling good or not so good
about right now.
It doesn't start with you. So it's really good to think about the things that
influence our perception and our version of reality so if we're own if we're
all of us we're seeing a slightly different version of reality we're seeing the
world slightly differently.
There's reasons for that there's reasons why.
One is our first relationship with caregivers so when we're born into this
world, we are like the most helpless mammals, I think on the planet.
We basically have, you know, the three trimesters and an extra trimester when
we come out so helpless in the world compared to other mammals.
And that we have to be completely cared for by another person, which means our
first instinct in the world is to communicate and to please another person, not
ourselves because that's the only way we can survive.
So when you think about that, that is our first conditioning that's the first
thing we have to do in this world is to please somebody else.
And as you get older, you know, that carries on for a few years you're totally
dependent on caregivers and it really shaped the way that your brain develops
and the way that you have to be in the world.
So a lot of us unless we've looked into it we're still coming with that same
conditioning was still coming with those same conditions are worth.
Another thing that shaped the way that you experience the world and your mental
health is society's expectations and oppression.
The categories that society puts on you so maybe it's race, class, culture,
gender, you know, obviously we're all working in camp or sex workers as well so
we are oppressed and there are expectations of us based on who other people say
we are.
And that of course influences our mental health and the way we feel about
ourselves.
Language is something that really shapes our reality. So, you know, for most of
us we grow up, even with the best if even if you had great childhood and you
know parents you weren't the best you.
It's likely that they said to you things like, Oh, you know, be a good girl,
you know, or, you know, if you fall over or you're not hurt it's so fine.
You're okay, which is switching you are from actually the fact that you are
actually hurt, you know, it's causing a distrust in yourself they telling you
something which is not your reality so that causes you not to believe yourself
anymore.
So language is really important.
And that's one thing that shapes our view of ourselves. And other people's
reactions to our needs, you know, if you grew up in a household where your mum,
for instance, was always really stressed or was always really sort of like, you
know, had a lot of things to juggle and was not managing so
then anything that you needed then might have been a huge inconvenience or, you
know, might have been snapped up, might have been angry, or whatever so that
you then the message given to you that your brain takes as data, you know, that
your brain
develops on is that my needs are not important, or actually my needs cause a
problem.
And so I need to suppress those I need to keep those to myself.
And our experiences, of course, our experiences all shape at version of reality
that we're living in our abilities so what we feel we can do.
And our friends family and community, which, you know, it can be a blessing and
a curse, of course we're here because we've got this lovely community which I
know has helped so many people.
And, and often, a lot of this stuff, a lot of this stuff can be contributed to
poor mental health but when we flip it, when we take control of it and when we
work on it, all of these things really can can set us up for great mental
health and really knowing and loving ourselves again.
So, all these things heavily influence how we see ourselves and whether or not
we love and prioritise ourselves, because in order to have good mental health,
prioritise our own needs.
And all this list of stuff is, you know, given us reasons throughout our lives,
especially as women and, you know, in certain situations where we're taught not
to prioritise our needs.
At certain age, and we're wondering why we're anxious or, you know, why things
aren't going so well.
And so, and the last one before I start the recording and then we'll have a
little share between ourselves.
So the good thing about all that, impressive all about but it's really good to
know, you know, why we are the way we are and what our influences are and why
we condition in a certain way.
The good thing is that mindset is a software that runs our life.
So the great thing is that like a software we can reprogram our mindset and
change our reality.
So, sometimes it runs a lot deeper. And if there is complex trauma there, you
know, if you've often been unsafe, or if your needs have not been met over a
long period of time, and that means emotional needs as well as physical.
Or there's been neglect or whatever, and sometimes more is needed, more is
needed than just this mindset shift, but it's a start, it's always a start.
And so, I can't see the top of that online.
Yeah, so your mindset is your app for life.
So if you think of the mindset of a software that runs your life, your mindset
determines how to how you manifest and interact with others, how you define who
you are, how you measure success, and what you do with your life.
So beliefs that are particularly important and I love this graphic, and self
believe so judging yourself to be capable of something vastly increases your
chances of success.
So some of the things you talked about in the last slide might have tuned you
off from your, your understanding your capabilities and believe it in yourself.
But some ways to overcome self doubt are to confront your inner critic, so that
little voice that comes up that tells you, you look fat, or you're not going to
do that or, you know, you just wasting your time is to confront it, is to
confront it, notice it, and stop giving it so much power.
Lean into your fears. So when we're scared of things we often avoid them, we
often avoid, or we change our behaviour so that we don't have to confront those
fears anymore, but leaning into those fears and actually finding out that you
can do things, and it's okay you can even when it's scary can be great.
So reaffirm and love yourself cut off negative people, and encourage others to
pursue their dreams as well I mean, as a psych therapist for me I get so much I
mean my mental health is just so affected by all the people that I help and all
the change I see in others it's amazing.
So, you know, altruism and helping others, and the other beliefs that are
important for your mindset or agency and personal responsibility.
So agency is a belief that you are in charge of your own life, which often
doesn't feel like when you've experienced trauma or when you've had, you know,
had really difficult experiences, but you can change this at any time with the
right support.
So if you don't like your circumstances then take the onus of making changes
don't look for someone else to blame, and that's difficult when you're blaming
yourself, because that's how you've been conditioned to be, but it can change,
it can always change and it's always just taking
the focus that the growth mindset is important, so set back to temporary
obstacles not failures and try harder to find a way.
And you know we all come across doors that slams that face or you know times
away embarrassed and things haven't gone right, but it's just finding a
different way isn't it finding another way in
that growth mindset.
And abundance, I love this one because it's really difficult I mean we're, we
're, another thing we're taught by society really is to be in competition with
each other, especially as women.
And so if you have an abundance mindset, there's plenty there for everyone we
're not in competition with the person next to us.
And there's enough, you know it will always come if we work towards it if we
believe it will come.
And an abundance mindset can and must be cultivated it says, so become aware
where you have scarcity mentality where you think that there's not enough it's
not going to happen it's not for you become aware of those thoughts.
Practice gratitude for what you already have.
Company of people with an abundance mindset and we all have that because I know
we have that in the group.
And, and focus more on goals then constraint.
So like we said in the manifestation it's a similar thing and that cool wasn't
it about focusing on what it's going to feel like and what it's going to be
like when you have the thing that you want, rather than right now you don't
have it focusing on the feeling of not having it.
That's what we expect.
And finally some big question so intentionally work to shape your beliefs about
these questions.
So who am I, why am I here, what will make me happy and even sometimes that's a
good question in the moment, like what will make me happy in this moment.
Why do bad things happen to good people so just some good questions to ask
yourself to sort of think about your mindset and switching it to.
So, with that, let's have a little check in so for anyone that wants to
absolutely don't have to and you can give as little or as much as you want.
But there's some prompts here, you know, if you want you could tell us how you
're feeling, tell us something you're grateful for, tell us what your needs
needs are today, something you need to accomplish today.
Maybe you could tell us, you know, one thing that you're struggling with at the
moment.
And then one thing that you're going to take on this call, one thing that you
're going to take going forward one thing that you're going to take
responsibility for and you know how you're going to help yourself with it today
.
I'm going to stop recording now.